I just want to start with a little bit of a word of warning, and that is:
أود البدء بتحذير بسيط، ألا وهو:
my job here tonight is to be a little bit of a "doctor bring-me-down."
أن مهمتي هنا الليلة هي أن أكون "الدكتور المحبط."
So bear with me for a few minutes, and know that after this,
لذلك تحملوني لدقائق معدودة واعلموا أنه بعد هذا،
things will get lighter and brighter.
ستجدون الأمور أكثر وضوحًا وإشراقًا.
So let's start.
لذا هيا نبدأ.
I know that many of you have heard the traveler's adage,
أعلم أن كثيرًا منكم قد سمعوا القول المأثور عن السفر:
"Take nothing but pictures, leave nothing but footprints."
"لا تأخذ شيئًا غير الصور ولا تترك غير آثار الأقدام."
Well, I'm going to say
حسنًا، سوف أقول
I don't think that's either as benign nor as simple as it sounds,
لا أعتقد أن الأمر بهذا اللطف والسهولة،
particularly for those of us in industries who are portraying people
خاصة للعاملين في المهن التي تتطلب وصف الناس
in poor countries,
في الدول الفقيرة،
in developing countries
والدول النامية،
and portraying the poor.
وتصوير الفقراء.
And those of us in those industries are reporters, researchers
وهؤلاء العاملون في هذه المهن هم المراسلون، والباحثون،
and people working for NGOs;
والعاملون في المنظمات غير الحكومية،
I suspect there are a lot of us in those industries in the audience.
أظن أنهم فئة كبيرة بين الجمهور.
We're going overseas and bringing back pictures like this:
حيث نسافر للخارج ونجلب صورًا كهذه:
of the utterly distressed
عن المنكوبين،
or the displaced
أو النازحين،
or the hungry
أو الجوعى،
or the child laborers
أو عمالة الأطفال،
or the exotic.
أو الأشياء الغريبة.
Now, Susan Sontag reminds us
الآن، تُذكرنا (سوزان سونتاغ)
that photographs, in part, help define what we have the right to observe,
أن الصور تبين لنا ما نملك الحق في مراقبته،
but more importantly,
ولكن الأكثر أهمية،
they are an ethics of seeing.
هو أنها تمثل أخلاقيات الرؤية.
And I think right now is a good time to review our ethics of seeing,
وأظن أن الوقت مناسب الآن لمراجعة أخلاقياتنا للرؤية،
as our industries of reporting and research and NGO work
بينما مهننا كمراسلين وباحثين ومنظمات غير حكومية
are collapsing and changing,
تنهار وتتغير،
in part, by what's being driven by what's happening in the economy.
بشكل جزئي بسبب ما يجرى في الاقتصاد.
But it's making us forge new relationships.
ولكنها تجعلنا نشكل علاقات جديدة.
And those new relationships have some fuzzy boundaries.
وهذه العلاقات الجديدة بها بعض الحدود الغامضة.
I worked at the edge of some of these fuzzy boundaries,
وقد عملت عند بعض هذه الحدود الغامضة،
and I want to share with you some of my observations.
وأود أن أشارك معكم بعض ملاحظاتي.
My ethics of seeing is informed by 25 years as a reporter
أخلاقيات رؤيتي مستوحاة من العمل 25 عامًا كمراسلة
covering emerging economies and international relations.
تغطي الاقتصادات الناشئة والعلاقات الدولية.
And I believe in a free and independent press.
وأنا أؤمن بصحافة حرة ومستقلة.
I believe that journalism is a public good.
وأن مهنة الصحافة هي للصالح العام.
But it's getting harder to do that job,
ولكن القيام بهذا العمل يصبح أصعب،
in part, because of the massive layoffs,
في جزء منه، بسبب تسريح العمالة الضخم،
because the budgets for international reporting aren't there anymore,
ولأن ميزانيات التقارير الدولية لم تعد موجودة،
new technologies and new platforms begging new content,
والتقنيات والمنصات الجديدة تسوق محتوى جديد،
and there are a lot of new journalisms.
وأصبح هناك أنواع جديدة من الصحافة.
There's activist journalism, humanitarian journalism, peace journalism,
هناك صحافة النشطاء، والصحافة الإنسانية، وصحافة السلام،
and we are all looking to cover the important stories of our time.
حيث نهتم جميعًا بتغطية الأحداث المهمة في عصرنا.
So we're going to NGOs and asking them if we can embed in their projects.
لذلك نذهب إلى المنظمات غير الحكومية ونطلب منهم الانضمام إلى مشاريعهم.
This is in part because they're doing important work in interesting places.
يحدث هذا جزئيًا لأنهم يقومون بعمل مهم في أماكن مثيرة للاهتمام.
That's one example here:
وهذا مثال لذلك:
this is a project I worked on in the Blue Nile in Ethiopia.
هذا مشروع عملت فيه في النيل الأزرق في إثيوبيا.
NGOs understand the benefits of having reporters tag along
تدرك المنظمات غير الحكومية فوائد وجود المراسلين
on their team.
في فريقهم.
They need the publicity, they are under tremendous pressure,
فهم يحتاجون إلى الدعاية، حيث يعملون تحت ضغط هائل،
they're competing in a very crowded market for compassion.
ويتنافسون في سوق مزدحم للغاية من أجل كسب التعاطف.
So they're also looking to reporters and to hire freelance reporters
لذلك يتطلعون أيضًا إلى المراسلين وتوظيف المراسلين المستقلين
to help them develop their public relations material
لمساعدتهم على تطوير علاقاتهم العامة
and their media material.
وموادهم الإعلامية.
Now, researchers are also under pressure.
الآن يتعرض الباحثون لضغوط أيضًا.
They're under pressure to communicate their science outside of the academy.
إنهم يتعرضون لضغوط لتوصيل علمهم خارج المؤسسات العلمية.
So they're collaborating with reporters, because for many researchers,
لذلك يتعاونون مع المراسلين، لأنه بالنسبة لكثير من الباحثين،
it's difficult for them to write a simple story or a clear story.
يصعب كتابة قصة بسيطة أو واضحة.
And the benefit for reporters
والفائدة للمراسلين
is that covering field research is some of the best work out there.
هي أن تغطية البحوث الميدانية من أفضل الأعمال المتاحة.
You not only get to cover science,
فلا تقتصر على التغطية العلمية،
but you get to meet interesting scientists,
لكنك تقابل علماء مثيرين للاهتمام أيضًا،
like my PhD advisor Revi Sterling,
مثل مستشارتي في الدكتوراه (ريفى سترلنغ)،
she, of the magic research high tops there.
وهي من أفضل الباحثين هناك.
And it was a discussion with Revi
وكانت المناقشة مع (ريفى)
that brought us to the edge of the researcher and reporter,
هي ما أوصلنا لحافة المراسل والباحث،
that fuzzy boundary.
هذه الحدود غير الواضحة.
And I said to her,
وقلت لها:
"I was looking forward to going to developing countries
"أتطلع إلى الذهاب إلى الدول النامية
and doing research and covering stories at the same time."
وعمل الأبحاث وتغطية القصص في نفس الوقت."
She said, "I don't think so, girlfriend."
فقالت: "لا أظن ذلك، عزيزتي."
And that confusion, that mutual confusion, drove us to publish a paper
وهذا الارتباك، هذا الارتباك المتبادل، دفعنا إلى نشر ورقة بحثية
on the conflicting ethics and the contradictory practices
عن الأخلاق المتضاربة والممارسات المتناقضة
of research and reporting.
في البحث والصحافة.
We started with the understanding
وبدأنا بفهم
that researchers and reporters are distant cousins,
أن الباحثين والمراسلين تربطهم قرابة بعيدة،
equally storytellers and social analysts.
فهم رواة قصص ومحللين اجتماعيين على حد سواء.
But we don't see nor portray developing communities the same way.
لكننا لا نرى ولا نصور المجتمعات النامية بنفس الطريقة.
Here's a very classic example. This is Somalia, 1992.
هذا مثال تقليدي للغاية. هذه هي الصومال عام 1992.
It could be Somalia today.
ويمكن أن تكون الصومال اليوم.
And this is a standard operating procedure
وهذا إجراء تشغيل قياسي
for much of the news video and the news pictures that you see,
لمعظم مقاطع الفيديو والصور الإخبارية التي ترونها،
where a group of reporters will be trucked in,
حيث يتم نقل مجموعة من المراسلين بالشاحنات،
escorted to the site of a disaster,
ويتم اصطحابهم إلى موقع الكارثة،
they'll produce their material, take their pictures, get their interviews,
فيقومون بإنتاج موادهم والتقاط صورهم وإجراء المقابلات،
and then they'll be escorted out.
ثم يتم اصطحابهم خارجًا.
This is decidedly not a research setting.
وهذه بالتأكيد ليست طريقة البحث.
Now, sometimes, we're working on feature stories.
الآن، في بعض الأحيان، نعمل على قصص إخبارية.
This is an image I took of a woman
هذه صورة التقطتها لامرأة
in Bhongir Village in Andhra Pradesh in India.
في قرية (بهونجير) في ولاية (اندرا برادش) بالهند.
She's at a microfinance meeting.
وهى في اجتماع تمويل أصغر.
It's a terrific story.
إنها قصة رائعة.
What's important here is that she is identifiable.
المهم هنا هو أنها قابلة للتحديد.
You can see her face.
تستطيعون رؤية وجهها.
This also is not a research picture.
وهذه ليست صورة بحث أيضًا.
This is much more representative of a research picture.
أما هذه فهي أكثر تمثيلًا لصورة البحث.
It's a research site: you see young women accessing new technologies.
إنه موقع بحث: ترون فيه النساء الشابات يستخدمن التقنيات الجديدة.
It's more of a time stamp, it's a documentation of research.
إنه أكثر من طابع زمني، إنه توثيق للبحث.
I couldn't use this for news.
لا يمكنني استخدام هذه في الأخبار.
It doesn't tell enough, and it wouldn't sell.
فهي لا تخبرنا بالكثير، ولا يمكن بيعها.
But then, the differences are even deeper than that.
ولكن الاختلاف أعمق من ذلك.
Revi and I analyzed some of the mandates that researchers are under.
قمت أنا و(ريفي) بتحليل بعض الصلاحيات التي يخضع لها الباحثون.
They are under some very strict rules
إنهم يخضعون لقواعد صارمة للغاية،
governed by their university research review boards
يحكمها مجالس مراجعة البحوث الجامعية
when it comes to content and confidentiality.
عندما يتعلق الأمر بالمحتوى والسرية،
Researchers are mandated to acquire document-informed consent.
فالباحثون مكلفون بالحصول على وثيقة موافقة.
Well, as a reporter, if I hang a microphone on someone,
حسنًا، كمراسلة، إذا علقت ميكروفونًا على شخص ما،
that is consent.
فهذه موافقة.
And when it comes to creating the story, I'll fact-check as a reporter,
وعندما يتعلق الأمر بإنشاء القصة، سوف أتحقق من الحقيقة كمراسلة،
but I don't invite company to create that story,
لكني لا أدعو شركاء لإنشاء هذه القصة.
whereas social scientists, researchers,
في حين أن علماء الاجتماع والباحثين،
and particularly participatory researchers,
وخاصة الباحثين المشاركين،
will often work on constructing the narrative with the community.
سيعملون عادة على بناء الرواية مع المجتمع.
And when it comes to paying for information,
وعندما نأتي لدفع ثمن المعلومات،
"checkbook journalism" is roundly discouraged,
فإن "دفتر شيكات الصحافة" مُحبِط للغاية،
in part, because of the bias it introduces in the kind of information you get.
في جزء منه، بسبب التحيز الذي يقدمه في نوع المعلومات التي تحصلون عليها.
But social scientists understand that people's time is valuable
لكن علماء الاجتماع يفهمون أن لوقت الناس قيمة،
so they pay them for that time.
لذلك يدفعون لهم عن ذلك الوقت.
So while journalists are well-placed
وبينما الصحفيون في وضع جيد
to convey the beauty of the scientific process --
للتعبير عن جمال النهج العلمي -
and I would add, the NGO process --
وأود أن أضيف، نهج المنظمات غير الحكومية -
what about the warts?
ماذا عن الثغرات؟
What happens if a research project is not particularly well-designed,
ماذا لو أن البحث ليس مصممًا بشكل جيد،
or an NGO project doesn't fulfill its goals?
أو أن مشروع المنظمة غير الحكومية لا يحقق أهدافه؟
Or the other kind of warts,
وماذا عن النوع الآخر من الثغرات،
you know, what happens after dark when the drinks happen.
تعلمون ما يحدث بعد حلول الظلام عند تناول المشروبات.
Research environments and reporting trips and NGO projects
بيئات البحث ورحلات المراسلين ومشاريع المنظمات غير الحكومية
are very intimate environments;
هي بيئات حميمة للغاية،
you make good friends while you're doing good work.
يمكنكم تكوين صداقات جيدة أثناء القيام بعمل جيد.
But there's a little bit of Johnnie Walker journalism after dark,
ولكن هناك القليل من صحافة (جوني ووكر) بعد حلول الظلام،
and what happens to that line between embedded
وما يحدث لهذا الخط بين المُتضمَّن
and in-bedded?
وما هو بين السطور؟
Or what do you do with the odd and odious behavior?
أو ماذا تفعل مع السلوك الغريب والبغيض؟
The point is that you'll want to negotiate in advance
النقطة هنا هي أنك سترغب في التفاوض مسبقًا،
what is on the record
حول ما يمكن نشره،
and off the record.
وما لا يمكن نشره.
I'm going to turn now to some NGO imagery
سوف أنتقل الآن لصور المنظمات غير الحكومية،
which will be familiar to some of you in this audience.
والتي ستكون مألوفة لبعضكم.
(Video) Narrator: For about 70 cents, you can buy a can of soda,
(فيديو) الراوي: مقابل 70 سنتًا، يمكنك شراء علبة صودا،
regular or diet.
عادية أو للحمية.
In Ethiopia, for just 70 cents a day,
وفي إثيوبيا، مقابل 70 سنتًا فقط في اليوم،
you can feed a child like Jamal nourishing meals.
يمكنك إطعام طفل مثل جمال بوجبات مغذية.
For about 70 cents, you can also buy a cup of coffee.
مقابل 70 سنتًا، يمكنك أيضًا شراء فنجان قهوة.
In Guatemala, for 70 cents a day,
وفي غواتيمالا، مقابل 70 سنتًا في اليوم،
you can help a child like Vilma get the clothes she needs to attend school.
يمكنك مساعدة طفل مثل (فيلما) للحصول على ملابس للمدرسة.
Leslie Dodson: Now, there's some very common imagery
(ليزلي دودسون): هناك صورة شائعة
that's been around for 40 years.
كانت موجودة طوال 40 عامًا.
That's part of Sally Struthers's famine campaign.
هذا جزء من حملة المجاعة ل(سالي ستروثرز).
Some of it is very familiar; it's the Madonna and child.
وبعضها مألوف جدًا. إنها (مادونا) والطفل.
Women and children are very effective in terms of NGO campaigns.
النساء والأطفال فعالون للغاية في حملات المنظمات غير الحكومية.
We've been looking at this imagery for a long time,
لقد كنا ننظر إلى هذه الصور لفترة طويلة،
for hundreds and hundreds of years; the Madonna and child.
لمئات ومئات السنين، (مادونا) والطفل.
Here is [Duccio],
ها هو (دوتشيو)،
and here is Michelangelo.
وهنا (مايكل أنجلو).
My concern is: Are we one-noting the genders
ما يقلقني هو: هل نحن منحازين لجنس
in our narratives of poverty in developing communities?
في قصصنا عن الفقر في المجتمعات النامية؟
Do we have women as victims, and are men only the perpetrators?
هل لدينا نساء كضحايا، وهل الرجال جناة فقط؟
Are they the guys with the AK-47s or the boy soldiers?
هل هم الرجال مع (الكلاشنكوف) أو الجنود الصبية؟
Because that doesn't leave room for stories
لأن ذلك لا يترك مجالاً للقصص
like the man who's selling ice cream at the refuge camp in Southern Sudan,
كالرجل الذي يبيع المثلجات في مخيم اللاجئين بجنوب السودان،
where we did a project,
حيث قمنا بمشروع،
or the stories of the men who are working on the bridge over the Blue Nile.
أو قصص الرجال الذين يعملون على الجسر فوق النيل الأزرق.
So I wonder:
لذلك أتساءل:
Are these stories inconvenient to our narratives?
هل هذه القصص لا تلائم رواياتنا؟
And what about this narrative?
وماذا عن هذه الرواية؟
This is a for-profit game,
هذه لعبة ربحية،
and its aim is to make development fun.
وهدفها هو جعل التنمية ممتعة.
One question is: Did they inadvertently make fun of?
وأحد الأسئلة هو: هل يسخرون من دون قصد؟
Another set of questions is: What are the rights of these children?
مجموعة أخرى من الأسئلة هي: ما هي حقوق هؤلاء الأطفال؟
What rights of publicity or privacy do they have?
ما هي حقوق الشهرة والخصوصية لديهم؟
Did they get paid?
هل يتقاضون أجرًا؟
Should they get paid?
هل يجب أن يتقاضوا أجرًا؟
Should they share in the profit?
هل يجب أن يشاركوا في الربح؟
This is a for-profit game.
إنها لعبة ربحية.
Did they sign talent waivers?
هل وقعوا على تنازلات الموهبة؟
I have to use these when I'm working with NGOs
يجب أن أستخدمها عندما أعمل مع المنظمات غير الحكومية
and documentary filmmakers here in the States.
وصناع الأفلام الوثائقية هنا في الولايات المتحدة.
In the States, we take our right to privacy and publicity
في الولايات المتحدة، نأخذ حقنا في الخصوصية والشهرة
very seriously.
على محمل الجد.
So what is it about getting on a long-haul flight
إذن ما الذي يجعل رحلة طيران طويلة
that makes these rights vaporize?
تجعل هذه الحقوق تتبخر؟
I don't want to just pick on our friends in the gaming arts;
لا أريد أن أصب تركيزي على أصدقائنا في فنون الألعاب فقط،
I'll turn to the graphic arts,
سوف أنتقل إلى فنون الرسم،
where we often see these monolithic, homogeneous stories
حيث نرى في كثير من الأحيان هذه القصص المتحدة والمتجانسة
about the great country of Africa.
عن دولة أفريقيا العظيمة.
But Africa is not a country, it's a continent.
لكن أفريقيا ليست دولة، إنها قارة.
It's 54 countries and thousands and thousands of languages.
إنها 54 دولة وآلاف اللغات.
So my question is: Is this imagery productive,
لذلك سؤالي هو: هل هذه الصور منتجة،
or is it reductive?
أم أنها اختزالية؟
I know that it's popular.
أعلم أنها شائعة.
USAID just launched their campaign "Forward" --
أطلقت الوكالة الأمريكية للتنمية الدولية للتو حملتها "إلى الأمام" -
FWD: Famine, War and Drought.
المجاعة والحرب والجفاف.
And by looking at it, you would think that was happening all the time,
وبالنظر إلى الأمر، ستعتقدون أن ذلك كان يحدث طوال الوقت
all over Africa.
في كل أفريقيا.
But this is about what's happening in the Horn of Africa.
لكن هذا حول ما يحدث في القرن الأفريقي.
And I'm still trying to make sense of Africa in a piece of Wonder Bread.
وما زلت أحاول أن أفهم لماذا أفريقيا في قطعة من خبز (وندر).
I'm wondering about that.
أنا أتساءل عن ذلك.
Germaine Greer has wondered about the same things and she says,
لقد تساءلت (جيرمين غرير) عن نفس الأشياء فتقول:
"At breakfast and at dinner, we can sharpen our own appetites
"في الإفطار والعشاء، يمكننا شحذ شهيتنا
with a plentiful dose of the pornography of war, genocide,
بجرعة وفيرة من المواد عن الحرب والإبادة الجماعية
destitution and disease."
والحاجة والمرض."
She's right. We have sharpened our appetites.
إنها محقة. لقد شحذنا شهيتنا.
But we can also sharpen our insights.
ولكن يمكننا أيضًا شحذ رؤيتنا.
It is not always war, insurrection and disease.
إنها ليست دائمًا الحرب والتمرد والمرض.
This is a picture out of South Sudan,
هذه صورة من جنوب السودان،
just a couple of months before the new country was born.
قبل شهرين فقط من ولادة البلد الجديد.
I will continue to work as a researcher and a reporter in developing countries,
سأواصل العمل كباحثة ومراسلة في الدول النامية،
but I do it with an altered ethic of seeing.
لكني أفعل ذلك بأخلاقيات رؤية معدلة.
I ask myself whether my pictures are pandering,
فأسأل نفسي إن كانت صوري خانعة،
whether they contribute to stereotypes,
أتساهم في نشر النمطية،
whether the images match the message,
هل تتطابق الصور مع الرسالة،
am I complacent or am I complicit?
هل أنا راضية أم متواطئة؟
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.